Finding Aid for Gunnar Birkerts and Associates, 1960-2014
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Duluth Public Library, Duluth, Minnesota 1966-1984, 699 drawings; 5 linear feet
  - Architectural Drawings
    - Library Building
      - Construction Documents
        - Final Design #3
          - Mechanical Drawings by Hoyem-Basso Associates, Inc., Mechanical and Electrical Engineers. Pencil and colored pencil drawings on electrostatic prints on mylar, 4/7/77, except as noted
            - Mechanical Details and Diagrams (M-10). Revised 12/20/1978 (Map-case 16, Folder 19)
            - Temperature Control Diagrams (M-11). Revised 12/20/1978 (Map-case 16, Folder 19)
            - Mechanical Schedules (M-12). Revised 03/13/1978 (Map-case 16, Folder 19)
            - Plumbing Riser Diagrams (M-13). 04/07/1977 (Map-case 16, Folder 19)
          - Electrical Drawings by Hoyem-Basso Associates, Incorporated, Mechanical & Electrical Engineers. Pencil drawings on electrostatic prints on mylar, 4/7/77, except as noted
            - Electrical Basement Floor Plan and Details (E-2). Revised 11/06/1978 (Map-case 16, Folder 20)
            - Electrical Ground Floor Plan (E-3). Revised 11/06/1978 (Map-case 16, Folder 20)
            - Electrical First Floor Plan (E-4). Revised 11/06/1978 (Map-case 16, Folder 20)
            - Electrical Second Floor Plan (E-5). Revised 11/06/1978 (Map-case 16, Folder 20)
            - Electrical Risers and Schedules (E-6). Revised 11/06/1978 (Map-case 16, Folder 20)
            - [Electrical Outlets for] Ground, First and Second Floors (E-1 to E-3). Three pencil drawings on reverse sepia prints, revised 08/04/1978 (Map-case 16, Folder 20)
          - Supplementary Construction Documents. Pencil drawings on reverse sepia prints
            - Ground Floor Reflected Ceiling Plan, Ceiling Joints at Lights (SKA-24). 01/23/1979 (Map-case 16, Folder 20)
            - First Floor Reflected Ceiling Plan, Ceiling Joints at Lights (SKA-25). 02/15/1979 (Map-case 16, Folder 20)
            - Second Floor Reflected Ceiling Plan, Ceiling Joints at Lights (SKA-26). 01/23/1979 (Map-case 16, Folder 20)
      - Shop Drawings
        - Representative Curtain Wall Drawings by H. H. Robertson Company. Forty-seven blue-line prints with red ink notations
          - EP-1, EP-1A, EP-2 to EP-14. Issued for approval 09/30/1977 (Map-case 16, Folder 21)
          - EP-15 and EP-16. Issued for approval 11/04/1977 (Map-case 16, Folder 21)
          - EP-17 to EP-36. Issued for approval 09/30/1977 (Map-case 16, Folder 21)
          - EP-39A and EP39-B. Issued for approval 11/04/1977 (Map-case 16, Folder 21)
          - EP-40, EP-43, EP-47, EP-52, EP-53. Issued for approval 09/23/1977 (Map-case 16, Folder 21)
          - EP-62. Issued for approval 01/04/1978 (Map-case 16, Folder 21)
          - RP-1. Issued for approval 05/19/1978 (Map-case 16, Folder 21)
    - Library Interiors Drawings
      - Schematic Design Presentation Drawings of Furnishings and Carpeting
        - Ground Floor, First Floor and Second Floor Plans. Three drawings with pantone color on black-line prints undated (Map-case 17, Folder 22)
        - [North Shore Rare Book Room Presentation Drawings], untitled. One ink on vellum drawing and one drawing with pantone color on black-line print undated (Map-case 17, Folder 22)
      - Design Development Interior Color Mock-Up Drawings
        - [First and Second Floor Perspectives], untitled. Three crayon drawings on black-line prints undated (Map-case 17, Folder 22)
      - Carpet Drawings
        - Ground Floor, First Floor and Second Floor Plans (C-1 to C-3). Dot screens and pencil drawings on three reverse sepia prints 03/21/1979 (Map-case 17, Folder 22)
      - Interior Furnishings Drawings. Pencil on mylar drawings 06/21/1979 except as noted
        - Ground Floor Plan (F-1) (Map-case 17, Folder 22)
        - First Floor Plan (F-2) (Map-case 17, Folder 22)
        - Second Floor Plan (F-3) (Map-case 17, Folder 22)
        - Elevations and Details (F-4) (Map-case 17, Folder 22)
        - Elevations and Details (F-5 and F-6). Two pencil drawings on reverse sepia prints 06/08/1979 (Map-case 17, Folder 22)
        - Duluth-North Shore-Minnesota Room Details (F-7) (Map-case 17, Folder 22)
        - Miscellaneous Details (F-8) (Map-case 17, Folder 22)
        - Audio-Visual Plan, Ground Floor (F-9) (Map-case 17, Folder 22)
        - Audio-Visual Plan, First and Second Floors (F-10) (Map-case 17, Folder 22)
      - Interior Signage Drawings
        - Signage Design Development Drawings. Ten pencil drawings on tracing paper; two ink and pantone color drawings on blue-line prints; and two pencil on vellum drawings undated (Map-case 17, Folder 23)
        - Dedication Plaque Design Development Drawings. Two pencil drawings on tracing paper and one pencil on vellum drawing undated (Map-case 17, Folder 23)
      - Interior Colors, Materials and Finishes. Samples of carpeting, paints, metal panels, wood panels, vinyl tiles, ceramic tiles and fabrics on two illustration boards undated (Map-case 17, Folder 24)
      - Interior Furnishings. Black and white and color photographs of furniture and samples of upholstery and wall coverings on four illustration boards undated (Map-case 17, Folder 25)
    - Fifth Avenue Mall and Plazas Drawings
      - Design Development Drawings
        - Site and Program Information Documents. Blue-line prints
          - Plan of Michigan Street to Superior Street (#1) by Aguar, Jyring, Whiteman, Moser. 3/67 (Map-case 17, Folder 26)
          - Plan of Superior Street to First Street (#2) by Aguar, Jyring, Whiteman, Moser. 3/67 (Map-case 17, Folder 26)
          - Existing Utilities, Fifth Avenue West Mall (#1) by Aguar, Jyring, Whiteman, Moser. 03/15/1967 (Map-case 17, Folder 26)
          - Site Development for the Radisson Duluth Hotel for the Greyson Mall Corporation by Damberg and Peck, Architects
            - Title Sheet and Detail Legend (#1) (Map-case 17, Folder 26)
            - Landscape and Parking Layout (#4) (Map-case 17, Folder 26)
        - Duluth Mall [Landscape Plans]. Two colored pencil drawings on black-line prints 06/25/1969 (Map-case 17, Folder 26)
        - Suggested Parking Lot and Site Development Revisions Proposed to the Greyson Mall Corporation. Two pencil on vellum drawings 10/18/1969 (Map-case 17, Folder 26)
        - Suggested Parking Lot and Site Development Revision Grading Plan and Partial Planting Plan. Two pencil on vellum drawings 10/27/1969 (Map-case 17, Folder 26)
        - General Paving and Sidewalk Furniture. Pencil on vellum drawing. 02/11/1970 (Map-case 17, Folder 26)
        - Partial Plan and Section, Utility Pole Elevation and Section and Light and Bench Plans, Elevation and Sections. Pencil on vellum drawing undated (Map-case 17, Folder 26)
        - East Plaza Plan and Section-Landscaping (A-107). Red pencil and ink drawing and sketches on blue-line print 03/04/1970 (Map-case 17, Folder 26)
        - Overall Plan of Fifth Avenue Mall and Plazas (DD-101). Photostatic copy 04/04/1970 (Map-case 17, Folder 26)
        - West Plaza (Upper Lower) Contour Plan, Phase One (DD-104). One reverse sepia print and one colored pencil and pencil drawing on tracing paper on blue-line print 03/20/1970 (Map-case 17, Folder 26)
        - West Plaza Paving Plan, Phase Two with Library Completion (DD-105). Reverse sepia print 04/14/1970 (Map-case 17, Folder 26)
        - West Plaza (Upper Lower) Section/Elevations (DD-106). Reverse sepia print 04/14/1970 (Map-case 17, Folder 26)
        - East Plaza Plan and Sections (DD-108). Reverse sepia print. 04/14/1970 (Map-case 17, Folder 26)
        - West Plaza (Upper Lower) Dimension Plan (DD-108). Pencil on vellum drawing undated (Map-case 17, Folder 26)
        - East Plaza [Plan and Sections] (DD-109). Pencil on vellum drawing undated (Map-case 17, Folder 26)
        - Pencil, colored pencil and ink drawings on tracing paper
          - Duluth Mall [Site Plans]. One dated 06/25/1969, one dated 10/2/69; and two dated, 10/16/1969 (Map-case 17, Folder 27)
          - Existing Grade at Wall. Undated (Map-case 17, Folder 27)
          - Raise Grade at Wall Two Feet. Undated (Map-case 17, Folder 27)
          - Parking Lot, 129 Cars Total. Undated (Map-case 17, Folder 27)
          - [Miscellaneous Site Plan, Landscape Plans and Elevations], untitled. Nine drawings undated (Map-case 17, Folder 27)
        - Presentation Drawings
          - [Landscape Plans], untitled. Tree cut-outs pasted on five black-line prints 10/03/1969 (Map-case 17, Folder 28)
          - [Fifth Avenue Mall Landscape Plans], untitled. Three colored pencil and ink drawings and notations on black-line prints 12/06/1969
            - Title page (Map-case 17, Folder 28)
            - Existing Conditions (Map-case 17, Folder 28)
            - Existing Street Elements (Map-case 17, Folder 28)
          - [East Plaza Site Renderings], untitled. One ink drawing and dot screen on vellum and one colored pencil and ink drawing on blue-line print undated (Map-case 17, Folder 28)
          - East Plaza [Site Renderings] (A-F). Six blue-line prints, presented 03/23/1970 (Map-case 17, Folder 28)
          - East Plaza [Site Renderings] (A-F). Seven blue-line prints 04/01/1970 (Map-case 17, Folder 28)
          - [Sidewalk Rendering], untitled. Ink drawing and dot screen on vellum undated (Map-case 17, Folder 28)
          - [Mall and Plazas Landscape Plans], untitled. Two ink on vellum drawings and nine colored pencil and colored marker drawings on blue-line prints undated (Map-case 17, Folder 28)
          - [Elevations], untitled. Colored pencil and colored marker drawing on blue-line print undated (Map-case 17, Folder 28)
        - [Miscellaneous Topographical Maps, Site Plans, Circulation Plans, Landscape Plans, Sections and Site Renderings], untitled. Twenty-five pencil or ink drawings on vellum and one ink drawing on reverse sepia print undated (Map-case 17, Folder 29)
      - Construction Documents
        - Architectural Drawings. Pencil on vellum drawings, 6/8/70, except as noted
          - Title Page, Key Plan, Index to Drawings and Legend (A-100) (Map-case 17, Folder 30)
          - Plan (A-101) (Map-case 17, Folder 30)
          - Plan (A-101). Colored pencil drawing on blue-line print (Map-case 17, Folder 30)
          - Mall, Partial Plan and Sections (A-102) (Map-case 17, Folder 30)
          - Mall, Partial Plan and Sections and Miscellaneous Details (A-103) (Map-case 17, Folder 30)
          - West Plaza Plan (A-104). Drawing with "superseded" in red ink 05/04/1970 (Map-case 17, Folder 30)
          - West Plaza Plan (A-104) (Map-case 17, Folder 30)
          - West Plaza Sections (A-105) (Map-case 17, Folder 30)
          - West Plaza Details (A-106) (Map-case 17, Folder 30)
          - East Plaza Plans and Sections (A-107) (Map-case 17, Folder 30)
          - East Plaza Room Section (A-107) undated (Map-case 17, Folder 30)
          - East Plaza Details (A-108) (Map-case 17, Folder 30)
          - Landscape Plan for West and East Plazas. 10/12/1971 (Map-case 17, Folder 30)
          - Landscape Details for West and East Plazas. 10/12/1971 (Map-case 17, Folder 30)
        - Structural Drawings by Robert A. Darvas and Associates, Structural Engineers
          - Key Plan, Retaining Walls (S-1). Sepia print 06/08/1970 (Map-case 17, Folder 30)
          - West Plaza Details (S-1-A). Pencil on vellum drawing 09/22/1970 (Map-case 17, Folder 30)
          - West Plaza, Curved Concrete Wall (S-2). Sepia print 06/08/1970 (Map-case 17, Folder 30)
        - Mechanical/Electrical Drawing by Aguar, Jyring, Whiteman, Moser, Inc., Mechanical/Electrical Engineers
          - Plan (M-E-1). Pencil drawing on sepia print 06/08/1970 (Map-case 17, Folder 30)
        - Construction Sign. Pencil on vellum drawing with reverse sepia print inset 08/19/1970 (Map-case 17, Folder 30)
    - Plaza Improvement Drawings
      - Design Development Drawings
        - Plaza Banners and Streetscape Drawings
          - [Site Plans, Floor Plans and Sections], untitled. Colored pantone and magazine photograph cut-outs on eight blue-line prints; one pencil on vellum drawing undated (Map-case 17, Folder 31)
      - Construction Documents
        - [Landscape and Street Furniture] (SKP-1), untitled. Pencil drawing on reverse sepia print with "superseded" in crayon undated (Map-case 17, Folder 32)
        - [Landscape and Street Furniture] (SKP-1), untitled. Pencil drawing on reverse sepia print 05/30/1978 (Map-case 17, Folder 32)
        - Plaza [Site Plan]. Pencil on vellum drawing 06/21/1978 (Map-case 17, Folder 32)
        - Plaza Improvements (PL-1). Pencil on vellum drawing 06/08/1979 (Map-case 17, Folder 32)
        - Plaza Improvements (PL-1). Pencil drawing on reverse sepia print, revised 10/03/1980 (Map-case 17, Folder 32)
        - Plaza Improvements (PL-2). Two pencil drawings on reverse sepia prints 06/08/1979, 10/03/1980 (Map-case 17, Folder 32)
        - Mall Details (DD-103). Pencil drawing on reverse sepia print, revised 10/03/1980 (Map-case 17, Folder 32)
        - [Partial Plans, Elevations and Sections], untitled. Two pencil on mylar drawings with "void" in red pencil undated (Map-case 17, Folder 32)
        - [Bench Plan, Section and Elevation] (SK-1A). Pencil on mylar drawing, revised 11/04/1982 (Map-case 17, Folder 32)
        - Bench Glue Laminate Alternate (SK-2A). Pencil drawing on reverse sepia print 11/04/1982 (Map-case 17, Folder 32)
        - Banner Retraction System Shop Drawing by Highamerica. Pencil notations on blue-line print 06/10/1981 (Map-case 17, Folder 32)
- State University of New York, College at Purchase, Dance Instructional Facility, Purchase, New York 1969-1997, 466 drawings; 5.5 linear feet
  Architect: Gunnar Birkerts and Associated
  Campus Master Plan Architect: Edward Larrabee Barnes
  Structural Engineer: LeMessurier Associates, Inc.
  Mechanical/Electrical Engineer: Jaros, Baum & Bolles
  Acoustical Engineer: Bolt, Beranek and Newman, Incorporated
  General Contractor: E. W. Howell Company
  Agreement Date: February 16, 1970
  Earliest Dated Drawing: February 23, 1970
  Latest Dated Drawing: August 31, 1976
  The Dance Instructional Facility of the State University of New York, College at Purchase (5.5 linear feet, 466 drawings; 1969-1997), designed in 1970 and completed in 1976, is significant because it is the first building in America devoted solely to the instruction and performance of dance and because it is an integral part of a campus master plan by Edward Larrabee Barnes for the new College at Purchase. Inspired by Governor Nelson A. Rockefeller's passion for the arts and his mission to create a statewide tertiary education system during the 1960s, the College at Purchase was built with funds from the 4 billion dollar State University Construction Fund and dedicated to the teaching of the fine and performing arts. Barnes developed a master plan reminiscent of Jefferson's mall at the University of Virginia and commissioned architects of national prominence to design buildings along the perimeter of his Great Court.
  Just as Mr. Birkerts was invited to join the illustrious company of I. M. Pei, Robert Venturi, Richard Meier, Kevin Roche and Cesar Pelli in his design of Lincoln Elementary School in Columbus, Indiana, so too at Purchase, his Dance Instructional Facility is in the company of academic buildings by such other renowned architects as Edward Larrabee Barnes, Philip Johnson/John Burgee, Paul Rudolph, Venturi and Rauch, The Architects Collaborative (Norman Fletcher), and Gwathmey, Henderson & Siegel. Commenting on the contribution of Mr. Birkerts' work to the new campus in his essay "The Architecture of Good Intentions" (1997), architectural critic Paul Goldberger states: "Only one architect, Gunnar Birkerts, is represented by a work equal to his best; his dance building is an exuberant structure of glass that seems to have managed to induce more creative energy out of Barnes' design structures than anything else on the campus has done".
  Mr. Birkerts' uses of metaphor and innovative lighting are hallmarks of his reputation for expressive design and are pivotal to our appreciation of the Dance Instructional Facility. Inspired by Dance Department Dean William Bales' vision of dance as ideally being performed out-of-doors, the architect conceived of the building as a garden, surrounded by a high wall, within which studios are positioned like pavilions. The sloped, glass top of the wall admits light to the linear, perimeter corridors and the interior studios, which in turn have their own inclined glass windows. Thus, natural light is diffused throughout the highly engineered learning and performance spaces, giving the artists a constant orientation to the world outside. The Barnes' master plan dictated a 130-foot frontage for all of the buildings along the Grand Court, as well as uniform materials of dark brick, tinted glass and anodized aluminum. Within the confines of these guidelines, Mr. Birkerts has designed a distinctive building which ennobles the art forms of dance and architecture.
  The Dance Instructional Facility at Purchase series includes 5.5 linear feet of textual records, which chronologically document the program, design and construction of the building, and 466 architectural and engineering drawings, which show the evolution of the design process through the "Schematic Design," "Design Development" and "Construction Document" sequences. The combination of the narrative and visual records gives researchers an unusually rich picture of the evolution of this building from conception to finish and an understanding of the complex management operations of a nationally prominent architectural firm in the 1970s.
  Researchers wishing to gain perspective on Mr. Birkerts' design of this project are encouraged to read the "Architect's Conceptual Statement" and the three critical articles which follow. The "Site and Program Information" and "Program Notebook" include the important background information about the College at Purchase, Barnes' master plan and the dance facility requirements which were gathered by Gunnar Birkerts and Associates during the early program phase of the project. Also of note in the narrative records of the series are the "Schematic Report" of 6/29/70 and the "Design Manual Report" of 12/11/70, which summarize the solutions found during the "Schematic Design" and "Design Development" phases of the architectural process and correspond to the drawings of these periods within the visual records. Likewise, the "Project Manual Specifications" of 7/16/3 are the architect's written requirements for the building, which, along with changes described in "Addenda #1-2" and "Bulletins #1-30," relate directly to the "Construction Documents" of the same date.
  The textual records of the Dance Instructional Facility series also document the evolution of the design and construction of the building from 1970 to 1976 through "Memoranda #1-129", "Minutes of Job Meetings #1-59," "Project Representative's Weekly Construction Reports #1-113", and "Correspondence In and Out" between the firm, client, contractor, and consultants. The narrative records also contain 98 8x10" black and white construction progress photographs of the project from 2/74 to 1/76. In addition to the written and graphic documentation available in this series, the photographs give us a third medium for understanding the evolution of this building.
  The visual records of this series include early, original pencil and ink "Schematic Design" drawings on vellum and tracing paper and original "Design Development" drawings. Blue-line and sepia prints are retained when they are substitutes for missing originals or when they contain annotations which further illuminate the design evolution of the building. Researchers should note that four conceptual sketches of the Dance Instructional Facility are housed in the Gunnar Birkerts Collection, which contains early drawings of most of his buildings by the architect's own hand. The finding aid for this second, collateral collection lists all of the conceptuals available for study.
  Also of interest within the visual records of this series are the 10 undated, ink on vellum "Presentation Drawings" which were exhibited at the Neuberger Museum of Art at Purchase College in 1996-1997. Original pencil on mylar "Construction Documents," with "Addenda" and "Bulletin" changes and dates noted on them, complete the visual documentation of this project. The Dance Instructional Facility and the academic buildings by other master architects which surround it on the 1970s S.U.N.Y. campus continue to hold fascination for scholars of architecture and planning.
  - S.U.N.Y., Purchase, Dance Instructional Facility Architectural Records
    - Architect's Conceptual Statement, from GA Architect 2: Gunnar Birkerts and Associates by William Marlin. Tokyo: A.D.A. EDITA Tokyo Co., Ltd., 1982 154 (Box 46)
    - Anderson, Jack. "Project for the 'Farthest-Out' College." Dance Magazine, February, 1969 (Box 46)
    - "The Architecture of the State University of New York at Purchase." Exhibition brochure 2/8/81-3/15/81 (Box 46)
    - "Urban/Suburban." Exhibition Essays by Bill Lacy and Paul Goldenberger, 9/22/96-1/19/97 (Box 46)
    - Project Staff Directories (Box 46)
    - Site and Program Information 1969-1970 (Box 46)
    - Program Notebook 10/21/1969, 11/12/1970 (Box 46)
    - Subsurface Investigation Reports to Edward Larrabee Barnes, Architect, I, II and III 06/07/1969 (Box 46)
    - State University Construction Fund's Architect's Agreement 02/16/1970 (Box 46)
    - Information Regarding Building Codes 1962-1971 (Box 46)
    - Consultant's Proposals 4/70-7/70 (Box 46)
    - Soil Borings Bid Proposals and Test Results 6/70-11/70 (Box 46)
    - Schematic Report 06/29/1970 revised, 09/16/1970 (Box 46)
    - Cost Estimates by Wolf and Company, Cost Consultants
      - July-September, 1970 (Box 46)
      - October 1970-December, 1971 (Box 46)
    - Information Regarding Bids for General Contract 12/69-10/73 (Box 46)
    - Outline Specifications 11/02/1970 (Box 46)
    - Design Manual Report 12/11/1970 (Box 46)
    - Specifications for Theatre, Library and Student Activities Building by Edward Larrabee Barnes, Architect 08/25/1971 (Box 46)
    - Project Manual (Specifications) 09/01/1971
      - Bidding Documents (Box 46)
      - Table of Contents and General Requirements (Box 46)
      - Site Work, Concrete, Masonry and Metals (Box 46)
      - Carpentry, Moisture Protection and Doors, Windows and Glass (Box 46)
      - Finishes, Specialties, Equipment and Special Construction (Box 46)
      - Conveying System, Mechanical and Electrical (Box 46)
    - Specifications for Miscellaneous Site Work by Peter G. Rolland and Associates, Site Planners and Landscape Architects 09/21/1971 (Box 46)
    - H.E.W. Federal Interest Grant Request 11/71-12/71 (Box 46)
    - Project Manual (Specifications) 07/16/1973
      - Bidding Documents (Box 46)
      - Table of Contents and General Requirements (Box 46)
      - Site Work, Concrete, Masonry and Metals (Box 46)
      - Carpentry, Moisture Protection and Doors and Windows (Box 46)
      - Finishes, Specialties, Equipment and Special Construction (Box 46)
      - Conveying System, Mechanical and Electrical (Box 46)
    - Addenda # 1 and #2 09/12/1973, 10/05/1973 (Box 46)
    - Memoranda
      - #1-50 3/2/70-2/22/71 (Box 47)
      - #51-100 3/3/71-2/6/75 (Box 47)
      - #101-129, 2/18/75-8/1/77 (Box 47)
    - Records of Bulletins, Claims and Field Orders 1/75-4/78 (Box 47)
    - Bulletins
      - #1-16 3/26/74-11/15/74 (Box 47)
      - #17-30 12/20/74-6/14/76 (Box 47)
    - Field Orders #1-17, 5/31/74-3/15/76 (Box 47)
    - Change Orders #1-39, 7/18/74-4/5/78 (Box 47)
    - Minutes of Job Meetings